<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Parlamento of Negrete (1803)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Translated from Spanish into English</resp>
               <persName>Elizabeth Contreras</persName>
               <persName>Pilar Herr</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofread and edited</resp>
               <persName>William Campbell</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded in TEI XML</resp>
               <persName>William Campbell</persName>
               <persName>Eleanor Withers</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Z">
                  <editor>José Manuel Zavala Cepeda</editor>
                  <title>Los Parlamentos Hispano-Mapuches, 1593-1803: Textos Fundamentales</title>
                  <publisher>Ediciones Universidad Católica de Temuco</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Temuco, Chile</pubPlace>
                  <date>2015</date>
                  <biblScope>pp. 413-423</biblScope>
                  <rs>Z</rs>
                  </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>  
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         
         <div n="1"><pb ed="#Z" n="413"/>
            <head><term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> of 1803. AGI, <placeName>Chile</placeName>, 204, folios 1-17.</head></div>

         <div n="2"><ab>In the field of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>, on the twenty-seventh day of the month of February, one thousand eight hundred and three: <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>, Brigadier General of the Royal Armies, Commander of the Infantry Battalion, and Commissioned by His Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Captain General to preside over the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> with the four Cantons or <span corresp="Indian">Indian</span> <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> stated: That as a result of the Measures issued previous to the Call and summons to the <term n="38">Congress</term>, he had prior notice that those <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> located mostly along the shores of  the Bío-Bío were to appear the first day of March, in accordance with the orders provided to them. On the same day, His Honor had traveled from the <term n="18" type="untrans" >Plaza</term> of Los Ángeles to the encampment with Troops of the Dragoon Corps, Artillery, and Militias destined for the garrison. Appearing upon his arrival, the <term n="7">Commissioner of Nations and General Language</term> and his Captains informed <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName> that all the Principal <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> of the <span corresp="Land">Land</span> were ready to greet him and receive his Orders. He declared that the twenty-eighth day of February and the first day of March should be established for the <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> and their Delegations to pass through the Fords of <placeName>Daguegue</placeName> and <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> to allow for the arrival of the <term n="17" type="untrans">Pehuenches</term> who, according to the news, were eagerly expected by everyone to appear together on the second day for the greeting and ceremony common in these instances. And, on the third day at six in the morning, the opening of the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> was to take place in the <term n="20" type="untrans">Ramada</term> intended for this purpose, the time of which would be announced by cannonade as a general proclamation for all. Thus it was dictated, commanded, and signed by his Honor ̶ <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName> ̶ <persName n="8">Gonzalo María de Figueroa</persName>.</ab></div>

         <div n="3"><ab>On the third day of March of this year, one thousand eight hundred and three, as a result of what was dictated in this Same document, after all the <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> with their <term n="42">Governors</term> and <term n="6" type="untrans">Capitanejos</term> had appeared on the previous day for the corresponding greetings with displays of the utmost satisfaction and joy, the previously planned general announcement took place at six in the morning. At the same time, the assigned Companies of Militias and of the Dragoon Corps of the <term n="32">Frontier</term> garrisoned the <term n="20" type="untrans">Ramada</term> of the <term n="15" type="untrans">Parla</term>.  Appearing in succession, <term n="42">Governors</term> of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, with two-hundred and thirty-nine <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> and several of their <term n="6" type="untrans">Capitanejos</term> and <term n="24">warriors</term> numbering more than a thousand people, placed themselves in their previously arranged seats and locations. <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>, Brigadier General of the Royal Armies, Commander of the Artillery Battalion and President of the <term n="38">Congress</term>, commissioned by and on behalf of His Excellency, <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="14">Luis Muñoz de Guzmán</persName>, <span corresp="Governor">Governor</span>, Captain General and President of the <term n="21" type="untrans">Real Audiencia</term> of this <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span>, appeared accompanied by <term n="23" type="untrans">Señores</term> Brigadier General <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="23">Pedro Nolazco del Río</persName>, Commander of the Dragoon Corps and General Military Headquarters of Los Ángeles; <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="16">Mariano de Roa</persName>, <term n="37">Archdeacon</term> of the Holy Cathedral Church of the City of <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName> on behalf of its Illustrious <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <persName n="21">Bishop</persName>; Colonels of Artillery <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="15">Manuel de Vega Bazán</persName> and <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="11">Juan Zapatero</persName>; <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="18">Melchor de Carbajal</persName>, Lieutenant Colonel of the Dragoon Corps; <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="22">Pedro José de Benavente</persName> of the same rank; <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="19">Miguel Puga</persName> and <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="13">Luis de la Cruz</persName>, <span corresp="Royal_Standard-Bearer">Royal Standard-Bearer</span> and Provincial Mayor, Deputies of the <term n="4" type="untrans">Cabildo</term> of the City of <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName>; the Reverend Father Guardian of the <term n="8" type="untrans">Colegio de <term n="29" type="untrans">Propaganda</term></term> Friar <persName n="7">Gil Calvo</persName>; and the Prefect of Missions Friar <persName n="6">Francisco Javier de Alday</persName> with six Religious Personnel and many other Parish Priests, Chaplains, and Political and Military Officers of this Army and Province. Finding all present, <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="8">Gonzalo María de Figueroa</persName>, Commission Secretary: Ordered that after general silence the customary oath be given by the <term n="7">Commissioner of Nations and General Language</term> to faithfully translate everything said by all parties. This having been executed by customary means, was assigned to the Reverend Guardian Fathers, Prefect, and Missionaries because of their language comprehension to ensure a faithful translation by which the officers carried out their duties, and His Excellency addressing the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> in the following manner stating:</ab></div>

         <div n="4"><ab>I have the greatest satisfaction, Principal <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> my Friends, to see all of you gathered at this Encampment today to celebrate the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> with the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> that encompass the Land from the Bío-Bío River in the South, to the most southern <span corresp="Nations"><term n="31">Nations</term></span> of the Continent, and from the Sea to the <term n="9" type="untrans">Cordillera</term>. All of you have requested this with the utmost seriousness, for the good of <span corresp="Your_Land">Your Land</span>. And His Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Captain General of the <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span> was eagerly looking forward to being present at this <span corresp="Port">Port</span> to ratify your obedience to our Grand King and Lord and to affirm all the Articles that would bring mutual happiness to both <span corresp="Nations"><term n="31">Nations</term>.</span> However, he has not been able to ratify it due to serious issues at the beginning of his Administration and other pending endeavors that have prevented him from being in attendance. Due to his legitimate reasons, he has kindly bestowed his authority on me so that on his behalf I preside over this <term n="38">Congress</term> in order to advise all of you on what is convenient to advance your interests, civility, and obedience to the King as good Vassals placed under his highest protection.</ab></div>

         <div n="5"><ab>Now, as I have witnessed the situation in <span corresp="Your_Countries">Your Countries</span> when a few years ago I traveled through the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapu</term> of <placeName n="2">Angol</placeName> to the Government of the <term n="18" type="untrans" >Plaza</term> of <placeName n="17">Valdivia</placeName>, which was full of estates, cattle of all breeds, advanced agriculture, strong <term n="14" type="untrans">mozetones</term> and families enjoying the tranquility and advantages that have been provided by the kindness of our beloved <term n="33">Sovereign</term> who has dispensed all means and considerations for your well-being, and as I have been shown all due respect and possible deference, I am proud to preside over this <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>. I express my heartfelt disposition to provide all the help that is fair and beneficial for everyone under the rules and Articles that you put forth in this same place to his Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <persName n="17">Marquess of <placeName n="9">Osorno</placeName></persName> in the year 1793, as well as other Articles that may be suitable to discuss for your own benefit, addressing the happiness of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, whose advantages have been proven by Brigadier Commander of the Dragoon Corps <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="23">Pedro Nolazco del Río</persName>, who has governed you for so many years with the utmost wisdom, and who wishes to see you achieving the pinnacle of your well-being and civilization. I trust that you will willingly follow my recommendations and obey my commands. I greet you all on behalf of the King and ask you to be mindful of the issues stated in this Document which includes only what is advantageous to you.</ab></div>
         
         <div n="6"><ab>I am confident that as a result of your understanding of my character and heart, which is committed to your well-being, you will do everything to preserve the unity in which I find you, burying in oblivion all disagreements and animosity that the <term n="11">Reductions</term> have previously held, strengthening the advantages hereby to bring about a general peace, that this <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> should mark a milestone from the distant past to your posterity, as the sole foundation of all your Agreements and of the protection of our <term n="33">Sovereign</term>, of which you will be worthy by virtue of your subordination and obedience.</ab></div>
         
         <div n="7"><head>Articles published in the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <span corresp="Chilean_Indians">Chilean Indians</span> assembled at <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> Field on the third, fourth and fifth days of March of one thousand eight hundred and three.</head></div>

               <div n="8"><ab>Being the first step of this <term n="38">Congress</term> to confirm their acknowledgement, and professing all to their Natural King and Lord, the Mighty and <term n="34">Sovereign</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="2">Carlos IV</persName>, and to his Successor his Serene Highness Prince of Asturias <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="4">Fernando</persName>, they ought to promise and swear to be faithful and obedient Vassals in all, and as such, friends of their friends and enemies of their enemies, without any cleverness other than that which corresponds to the simple words that foreshadow what will be stated in the following Articles:</ab></div>
         
               <div n="9"><ab>That having discussed in the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName>Lonquilmo</placeName> the methods to establish the markets, which would facilitate the sale of goods earned by commerce by the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, which was unproductive due to loss and delays that resulted from waiting on the time periods specified in that decision: The same case was discussed again, for their sole benefit at the <span corresp="last_Parlamento_of_Negrete">last <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>,</span> expanding free trade that all the <term n="36">natives</term> could carry out in all <term n="18" type="untrans" >plazas</term>, villages, and cities of the <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span>, freely moving through all of our roads and lands, with the goods they transport, and in the same manner the Spaniards through theirs, crossing the roads reciprocally, free, and with the utmost self-assurance; which resolution was signed, and consequently presented to his Excellency for his <term n="34">Sovereign</term> approval, which was indeed obtained and established in the past year of 1796 under the regulations indicated by the public Announcement of this specific matter. This resulted in major advantages for the <term n="36">natives</term>, as they have experienced it, and I witness with pleasure a beginning of their civilization, peacefulness, and an increase of their interests, whose serious motives seek their acknowledgement by the mercy of the King, ratifying unanimously their Treaty.</ab></div>
         
         <div n="10"><ab>That it was also mandated across all the <span corresp="land">land</span> (it was the third Article in the <span corresp="last_Parlamento_of_Negrete">last <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>),</span> that the sons of the <term n="42">Governors</term>, <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> or <span corresp="Principal_Indians">Principal Indians</span>, receive a Christian education at the Seminary that his Excellency funds in the City of <placeName n="6">Chillán</placeName>, whose advantages are known by experience, having under consideration many sons of the <term n="36">natives</term> of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> placed in the highest honor of the Priesthood, with devotion and due respect, and other convenient opportunities that have provided them a good education; because of the latter, it is emphasized again, that all the good <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> reinforce their commitments by giving their sons to the Reverend Missionary Fathers and Teachers of said School, for the proposed purposes in which I will have the highest satisfaction, and will provide evidence of their consideration of my Recommendations.</ab></div>
         
         <div n="11"><ab>That having been also discussed in the <span corresp="Parlamento_of_Lonquilmo"><term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName>Lonquilmo</placeName>,</span> and authenticated in the <span corresp="last_Parlamento_of_Negrete">last <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>,</span> about the disagreements, thefts and bloody <term n="13" type="untrans">malocas</term> that have taken place among some Factions of the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>. And, seeing them today all together in peace, and all dedicated to the work and opportunities of life, it greatly satisfies me to charge and mandate to them, that having completely forgotten all resentment, to treat each other from now on as friends, brothers and peers; and that whoever alters this behavior, or takes up arms to rob and take revenge, breaking this Treaty against the respect owed to the <term n="34">Sovereign</term> authority, will be considered a rebel and punished with all the force that corresponds to bad vassals, and enemies of their own blood.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="12"><ab>That the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> were also warned in the <span corresp="previous_Parlamento">previous <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>,</span> neither to allow nor to provide shelter in their lands to Spaniards, villains or Thieves, who having freed themselves of the punishment deserved by their crimes, flee to <span corresp="the_land">the land</span>; and it is emphasized again never to admit them, but on the contrary to inform of their whereabouts or take them to the jails of the corresponding <term n="18" type="untrans" >plazas</term>, villages and cities, and especially for the deserters from the Precinct of <placeName n="17">Valdivia</placeName>, imitate the <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> of <placeName>Toltén</placeName> and that part of the south, who go after and deliver them to their <term n="42">Governor</term>, considering them as enemies of their estates and of public safety. It is duly requested again to apprehend these villains, assuming that for each one delivered to any of the <term n="19" type="untrans">Plazas de la Barrera</term>, they will receive twelve <term n="28" type="untrans">pesos</term>, according to the aforesaid agreement in the <span corresp="previous_Parlamento">previous <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>.</span></ab></div>
         
         <div n="13"><ab>That the sea being found full of foreign vessels on the pretext of whale hunting, <span corresp="they">they</span> cunningly enter <span corresp="their">their</span> coasts, as has already occurred on the coasts of <placeName n="15">Tirúa</placeName> in the last years of the <span corresp="war_with_the_British_Nation">war with the British <term n="31">Nation</term>,</span> they should not permit this under any circumstances, in compliance with the King’s orders, and also because of serious harm that would result from negotiating with some <term n="31">Nations</term> that only aspire to enter <span corresp="their">their</span> lands, becoming their owners, with the destruction of its inhabitants, as illustrated by experience. In addition, that in case of war with any foreign <term n="31">nation</term>, they ought, as good vassals, to attend personally to the defense of these dominions of His Majesty, whenever they may be attacked, according to what has been agreed to and sworn by the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, who now are being reminded of their obligation, with the aim that when the situation arises, they come forward armed and mounted to unite with the troops of the King, under the orders of their chiefs, and hinder any attempt to disembark on the coasts of this <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span> through the duration of these expeditions, with the <term n="31">nations</term> provided in such cases to all the Spanish troops, corps and militias.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="14"><ab>That being forbidden according to the fifteenth Article of the <span corresp="last_Parlamento_of_Negrete">last <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>,</span> all incursions through the <term n="30" type="untrans">pampas</term> of <placeName n="5">Buenos Aires</placeName> and trade in those provinces, and seeing through experience the thorough compliance given by the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> to this Treaty, it is recommended to them the continuation of their respect and subordination to the orders of the King, and the trade by the <term n="36">natives</term> in that Viceroyalty, that I already see established, and with the least loss to both <term n="31">nations</term>.</ab></div>
         
               <div n="15"><ab>That, lastly, the mercy of our <term n="33">Sovereign</term> embraces all the interests of these <term n="36">Natives</term> his Vassals and wishes the happiness that results for them from the peace and free trade amongst themselves and the Spaniards, as children of the same father, and also above all wishes them eternal happiness. To this end, he opens his treasuries, and with unspeakable cost brings from Spain the Missionary Fathers to these lands, not to seek gold, silver nor <term n="27">estates</term>, but for their protection, and to teach them all the ways to Heaven, helping them with good advice to maintain and preserve peace, and enhance it. To which effect they are urged to greatly respect and appreciate the Fathers and not only to allow them passage through their lands, but also welcome them there. Although, they are not forced to do so, and this is solely a recommendation coming from the good heart and desires I have for the good of all the <term n="36">Natives</term>, and therefore I repeat to them, that when the Missionary Fathers pass through the land, they are not there for trade nor for any other ends but for their love for the <span corresp="Indians">Indians</span>, to assist them where they have missions and friendly dealings with all the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> as mandated by His Majesty and myself. As proof of the respect I have for them, I give them this advice, also charging them to see them [Missionary Fathers] with all respect and attention, and in particular the Reverend Father Prefect whom His Majesty has designated as the head of all the missions, with a special request to direct all their tasks and efforts to the good of the land, favoring and educating his <term n="36">natives</term> on the road to Heaven, for them to obtain all the spiritual and temporal happiness, as wished by his fatherly heart; and to this end I charge them again always to admire and to respect him.</ab></div>
         
         <div n="16"><ab>At this point, permission was requested by the <term n="5" type="untrans">Cacique</term> <term n="42">Governor</term> of the Christian <term n="11">Reduction</term> of <placeName n="12">Santa Fe</placeName>, <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="9">Ignacio Nagpayluan</persName> according to the traditional privilege he has in these cases. Permission granted, he addressed his speech to all the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> in attendance, proposing to them the appointment of the one who is responsible for receiving the responses from the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, which fell by unanimous vote upon on the <term n="42">Governor</term> of the <term n="11">Reduction</term> of <placeName n="2">Angol</placeName> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="5">Francisco Curinagüel</persName>. Subsequently, he gathered up the ceremonial canes, and laid on top of them that of the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> President of the <term n="38">Congress</term>, and right below that of the Brigadier Commander of the Dragoon Corps, he tied all of them together with the one belonging to the <term n="7">General Commissioner of Nations</term>. He called all <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> to attention, communicating to them in detail what His Majesty had expressed and the content of the aforementioned Articles, encouraging them to a timely compliance. And, fully informed, <term n="42">Governor</term> <persName n="5">Curinagüel</persName> said: That the selection made by his Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Captain General for Brigadier <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName> to preside over the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> was of the utmost satisfaction and liking of the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, and especially the pious remembrance announced to them of their King and Lord in reiterating all of the Articles and Treaties of the <span corresp="previous_Parlamento">previous <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>,</span> whose arguments had been heard with particular attention by the <term n="7">General Commissioner of Nations</term>, that were only conducive to the good and advantage of the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>. And for this reason, their recognition of the King was great, and together with all the land they were gladly willing to obey and ratify them [the articles], encouraging all the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> to anticipate the state of happiness already present by the means provided to them and that is essential for their well-being and peace.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="17"><ab>The <term n="5" type="untrans">Cacique</term> <persName>Tranamilla</persName> of the <term n="11">Reduction</term> of <placeName n="14">Temulemu</placeName>, reiterating what he had heard from the President of the <term n="38">Congress</term>, said: That everything was of the utmost benefit to the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> and the public interest; thus they ought to strive to continue the happiness that found them through the correct rulings of the ministers of the King, who felt very sorry for them [the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>], and that <persName n="5">Curinagüel</persName> and all present made efforts to recognize in the actual ceremony their recognition of, and willingness to maintain, their obedience to all that is ordered of them.</ab></div>
               
               <div n="18"><ab>A hundred and more <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> spoke in those same terms, more or less, with such lively expressions of recognition that confirmed the good disposition of their hearts to obey all that had been agreed upon before. And, being already four in the afternoon, they begged for the <term n="15" type="untrans">Parla</term> to end, to be continued the following day; this being approved by his Lordship, he retired with his entourage and signed. - <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>. - <persName n="8">Gonzalo María de Figueroa</persName>.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="19"><ab>On the fourth day of said month and year, having made the established announcement by cannonade, at the same time as the previous day, and gathering promptly the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> in the <term n="20" type="untrans">ramada</term>, his Lordship proceed with his entourage, and taking his seat, received the greeting and courtesies customary to the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>. The <term n="42">Governor</term> <persName n="5">Curinagüel</persName> continued with the same terms as the previous day, with the remainder of those who had not received his words, whose <term n="15" type="untrans">parla</term>, and reply of one-hundred and twenty-seven <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>, lasted until four thirty in the afternoon. All of them participated with their utmost willingness to maintain themselves faithful, to improve reciprocal trade, keeping open their roads as a basis of this treaty and especially to all the missionary fathers who might freely travel through their lands, that <span corresp="they_would_carry_them">they would carry them</span> in their arms, if necessary, with all due respect and love; and, that the same would be done with the Spaniards according to what had been agreed upon, promising to comply unanimously with all the Articles and recommendations that had been communicated to them on behalf of their King and Lord, ratifying fidelity to his <term n="35">Sovereignty</term>. Lastly, requesting to halt the ceremony because they were very fatigued, to which his Lordship agreed, proceeding to tell them that for the next day, that due to their terms and advice, he would guarantee the interest he had in their faithfulness, with them giving proof of their good intentions and obedience, and confirming that all was in order he signed.- <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>.- <persName n="8">Gonzalo María de Figueroa</persName>. </ab></div>
         
         <div n="20"><ab>On the fifth day of said month and year, having made the established announcement by cannonade, just as on the previous days at the same time, and gathered the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> in the <term n="20" type="untrans">ramada</term>, his Lordship proceeded with his entourage, and taking his seat, received the greeting and courtesies as on the previous days from the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>. At this time, <term n="42">Governor</term> <persName n="5">Curinagüel</persName> got to his feet and addressed his Lordship with the following reasoning: Ten years have passed since the land convened in this same place to celebrate a <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> in the presence of his Excellency the <persName n="17">Marquess of <placeName n="9">Osorno</placeName></persName>, whose Treaties and recommendations have been fulfilled with the greatest scrupulousness, and, in particular those that seek the free and reciprocal trade that brings so many advantages to the common good--even though, in the <term n="11">Reductions</term> of <placeName>Boroa</placeName>, and others, there has been no shortage of troubles and uneasiness, as if the authority of the <term n="25">caudillos</term> does not have the required strength to contain them. Nevertheless, they [the troubles] have vanished, improving public safety, agriculture, cattle ranching, and providing commerce to the extent of the capacity of the few available routes for trading, whose advantages have filled them with opportunity, having completely forgotten the <term n="13" type="untrans">malocas</term> that previously caused so much harm among the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> themselves, arriving today at the height of peace. This has been achieved by them by having fulfilled the Treaties and recommendations they received in said <term n="38">Congress</term>, and more that have been continuously provided to them, and the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> having been in attendance to celebrate on these days the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> they requested. They have heard with the utmost pleasure everything that was proposed to them on the first day of its opening, and by all means thanking His Majesty for the benefits dispensed to them and offered on behalf of all the <span corresp="Land">Land</span> to fulfill the Treaties in general, and each of them in particular, as ways to ensure the peace and calm they have obtained and experienced.</ab></div> 
 
         <div n="21"><ab>The <term n="5" type="untrans">Cacique</term> <term n="42">Governor</term> of <placeName>Maquehue</placeName> <persName>Vilumilla</persName>, his Brother <persName>Coigüengir</persName>, <persName>Chicaguala</persName>, <persName>Pichunman</persName> and others, said that on behalf of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> gathered there, they pleaded with respect to the distance of the location of the School of instruction for their sons. They desired for it to be founded on this <term n="32">frontier</term> in the Village of <placeName n="18">Los Ángeles</placeName>, to be able to see them on occasion, and in this manner the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> endeavor to gladly offer their youths to the education provided by the <term n="34" select="2">Sovereign</term> mercy included in these benefits.</ab></div>
               
               <div n="22"><ab>The <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> <term n="17">Pehuenches</term> of <placeName>Callaqui</placeName>, <placeName n="10">Quilaco</placeName> and <placeName>Hinquin</placeName>, named <persName>Coliman</persName>, <persName>Liupay</persName> and <persName>Coigueman</persName>, said: That they had heard in recent years that the <term n="31">Mission Home</term> located in <placeName n="11">Santa Bárbara</placeName> was going to be relocated, and this being the source from where the benefits for the <term n="17">Pehuenches</term> previously had originated. They pleaded not to alter it but to maintain it for the same purposes, with respect to the good disposition that <term n="17">Pehuenche</term> <persName>Millalem</persName> of <placeName>Lonco</placeName>, and other Faction members presented to them being of the utmost benefit as well, and primarily to the sons that the missionary fathers educate there.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="23"><ab>The <term n="5" type="untrans">Cacique</term> <persName>Millalem</persName> of <placeName>Cura</placeName>, on the advice of his Faction members <persName>Guegnir</persName>, <persName>Pagitur</persName> and others, said: That for some time he has desired to invoke the footsteps his Father took, requesting again the mission that he had in <placeName>Lolco</placeName>. However, this has not been resolved as of yet, because of the <term n="13" type="untrans">malocas</term> and disagreements they have had in previous years with the Eastern <term n="17">Pehuenches</term> that have been cleared entirely, and reconciled, in hopes of [the mission] being founded as of next spring in his former country. And now therefore he asks to be granted missionary fathers to confirm that they be reestablished. The <term n="11">Reduction</term> of <placeName n="12">Santa Fé</placeName> composed of its <term n="42">Governor</term>, and <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term>, with those of <placeName n="2">Angol</placeName>, <placeName>Maquegua</placeName>, <placeName>Lebcoyan</placeName>, and in general most of those of the <span corresp="land">land</span> pleaded for the request their deceased <term n="42">Governor</term> <persName>Levigueque</persName> made in the General <span corresp="Parlamento...1793"><term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>, the previous year of one thousand seven hundred and ninety-three,</span> to be granted Missionaries of <term n="29" type="untrans">Propaganda</term> in place of the Priest assigned to them, as of the utmost spiritual need.  And furthermore, because the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> have communicated their utmost willingness for the fathers, and said post, from where the missions originated and expanded through the <span corresp="land">land</span>, where their superior resided. With this step, they could confirm the same for the future, which they consequently emphasized collectively with the utmost determination.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="24"><ab>The <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> <term n="42">Governors</term> of <placeName n="3">Arauco</placeName>, <placeName n="16">Tucapel</placeName>, <placeName n="15">Tirúa</placeName>, and <placeName n="4">Boca de Imperial</placeName>, and likewise those of <placeName n="2">Angol</placeName>, <placeName>Repocura</placeName>, <placeName>Maquegua</placeName>, <placeName n="19">Chacaico</placeName>, and in general all of those of the <placeName>Llanos</placeName>, said: That free trade Treaties were in place, and roads open to all places. They only pleaded that they [the Spaniards] not permit thieves to cross into <span corresp="their_lands">their lands</span> through the <term n="19" type="untrans">Plazas de la Barrera</term>, but rather that trade be done by honest men to avoid any disagreements, prohibited as such by his Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Captain General, to whom they repeated this supplication. And with regard to faction members, <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> or <term n="14" type="untrans">mozetones</term> that cause disorder or <term n="13" type="untrans">malocas</term> in the <span corresp="land">land</span>, it is up to the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> to punish them, as common enemies, as well as of their own blood, as illustrated by Article four of this matter. And regarding criminals and convicts from Valdivia who desert the Spaniards and seek refuge in <span corresp="their_lands">their lands</span>, not to be permitted by the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> and to be handed over by them as required, because they are really the plague of the <span corresp="land">land</span> because of their poor behavior and habits.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="25"><ab>In a similar manner the <term n="42">Governors</term> of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> stated, together with all the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> in attendance, that under no circumstances will they permit on their coasts either vessels or foreign peoples, as had already been established in other <term n="16" type="untrans">parlamentos</term>. They did not ignore their vicious intentions, and that the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> of <placeName n="3">Arauco</placeName>, <placeName n="16">Tucapel</placeName>, <placeName n="4">Boca de  Imperial</placeName>, and the sea shores up to <placeName n="17">Valdivia</placeName>, ought to be the most zealous, as the most invested and that the rest of the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> would gladly help with whatever case of this nature in the future. Additionally, with respect to trade and impeccable behavior in the <term n="30" type="untrans">Pampas</term> and the Provinces of <placeName n="5">Buenos Aires</placeName>, they have proven in good faith in recent years, that they will continue with the utmost effort. Consequently, some <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> and <term n="6" type="untrans">capitanejos</term> requested security documents in order to enter those countries with their <term n="10" type="untrans">ponchos</term> and other goods of trade. And lastly, they desired nothing more than to prove by their obedience the respect they have for the good counsel they have received, and repeatedly receive, whose enforcement the good <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> are convinced results in the peace and benefits they presently have.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="26"><ab>The <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> President of the <term n="38">Congress</term>, after having heard the long declaration of their responses, and the readiness displayed to comply with everything that had been proposed to them, he said: That he was very pleased to see them express themselves in such an articulate and obedient manner about what had been proposed to them, all pointing to the well-being of the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, that greatly emphasized the mercy of our beloved <term n="33">Sovereign</term>. However, having had news that in other <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamentos</term> the same gestures and offers had been made, but after [the Mapuches] failing to abide by many Treaties to the detriment of most of them and of their own interests, he desired that the current <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>, as he proposed to them on the first day, become an irrevocable foundation of their Treaties. The contrary would be to provoke the powerful punishment of His Majesty, and result in the elimination of these <term n="38">Congresses</term> or <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamentos</term>, which are terminated when the outcomes are not assured on their part. And it being his [the President's] role to announce the truth to the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>, his friends, manifesting to all his desire for their success: lastly, and as proof of his feelings of humanity that assist him for the good of the <term n="36">natives</term>, he wanted to advise them, and he hoped that they would accept and comply with his advice, leaving them with this reminder:</ab></div>
               
         <div n="27"><ab>That when he passed through the <span corresp="land">land</span> in previous years when he was assigned to the Government of Valdivia, he received news and through experience he witnessed the extent of the cruelty placed by the Devil in the mouths of some liars alleged to be fortune tellers, who ascribe the natural death of men to spells and witchcraft of some wretched men or women. <span corresp="They_accuse_the_latter">They accuse the latter,</span> and based solely on their statement proceed to the bloodiest and the most unjust carnage of which there is unknown precedent: And wanting to dissuade them [the lying fortune-tellers], and henceforth cause them to forget such cruelty against their own kind, he pleaded with them to be persuaded that death is the end of all men since our forefathers and that this inhumane and cruel behavior should be eradicated in all the land. In the event that anyone should attempt a similar atrocity in the future, he should be hampered by the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>, and they should rescue the victims destined for the knife or fire and hand them over to the commanders of the Barrera, for which they will be properly rewarded as defenders of humanity. He hoped for his advice to be acknowledged and followed by the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, charging the <term n="7">General Commissioner of Nations</term> and captains, to guard and to warn of any unexpected infraction and deal with as is deserved by the aggressor of such brutality.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="28"><ab>All the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> listened attentively to this advice, and conversing amongst themselves, they said: That it was proof of the good heart of their superiors, and especially the one who presided over the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>, that they, for their part, were convinced henceforth to prevent those cruel acts and the <term n="42">Governors</term> of <placeName>Curinagüel</placeName>, <placeName n="3">Arauco</placeName>, <placeName n="16">Tucapel</placeName> and others forced all the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> to please the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> President of the <term n="38">Congress</term>, and to deliver in case of any extreme situation, every man or woman slandered as witch or sorcerer, to be charged with never returning to the land.</ab></div>
               
         <div n="29"><ab>Indeed, they ratified their promises, that they would not break them, being disposed toward any mandates asked in the service of the King and their common good and that of the Spaniards. They pleaded as the <term n="38">Congress</term> came to an end that a cannonade be made for all to express their happiness and recognition of the King, for on that day that they had arrived at the pinnacle of trust built by their negotiation with the Spaniards, and for the repeated proofs they have of their [the Spaniards'] good hearts. His Lordship, having concluded this ceremony, charged that they all pledge vassalage and fidelity to their way of life. This was verified by the <span corresp="Christian_Indians">Christian Indians</span> swearing on the Holy Cross, and the <span corresp="heathens">heathens</span> raising an arm (all bending the knee) and recognizing as their natural King and Lord the Mighty King of the Spanish territories the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="2">Carlos IV</persName> and his immediate successor his Serene Highness Prince of Asturias <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="4">Fernando</persName>. And [they pledged] that they would scrupulously guard the Treaties and Counsels of this <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> and of the previous one, which was verified with the utmost respect and general happiness by the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>. The fifteen-cannon salute took place, repeating all Hail to the King, and embracing with special joy and affection the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> President of the <term n="38">Congress</term>, all present and amongst themselves. The Lords in attendance were mandated to affirm that if to disseminate from this place to the interior of the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapu</term> of <placeName n="2">Angol</placeName> were convenient for any <term n="31">Mission Home</term>, this will be granted to them after they acknowledge and establish their promises in their own Lands, to which they do not appear to agree. <!--whc 01-AUG-2023: waiting to hear back from Word comment before I fix the previous sentence--> That the <term n="7">Commissioner of Nations</term> convey to the <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, during the Councils they will hold next spring, to spread to all their factions the Treaties of this <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>, the great satisfaction I [the President of the Congress] have as a result of their acceptance of the counsels and mandates the Lord my commissioner gave them at that <term n="38">Congress</term>, these being related to the preservation of their peace, and reciprocal unity, and of their fidelity to the Spaniards by clearing their roads to Valdivia, protection of their coasts against common enemies, cessation of incursions into the <term n="30" type="untrans">pampas</term> of Buenos Aires, devoting themselves to work and cultivation of their lands to live happily with their families. And that I promise thorough compliance and to have the contentment to provide to them every benefit, protection, and justice that depend on my authority, according to the benevolent intentions of the <term n="33">Sovereign</term>, as he has done before, listening to their fair claims that have taken place since I assumed the High Command of this <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span>. And now, on occasion of this <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>, all in attendance have been sent an abundance of presents, and the <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> with the largest entourage and most reputable behavior have been assigned a fixed allowance financed by the <term n="22" type="untrans">Real Hacienda</term> through the immense generosity of the King. He has commissioned for them to be treated with the utmost humanity and courtesy; hence they ought to acknowledge him as a father and pay their most humble tributes to all the commanders who on behalf of his Royal name govern this <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span> and its <term n="32">frontier</term>. Finally, offering well-deserved thanks to the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Brigadier <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>, Commissioner President, for his good execution and the advantageous results of this ceremony, no less to the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Brigadier <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="23">Pedro Nolazco del Río</persName>, Commander of the <term n="18" type="untrans" >Plaza</term> of Los Ángeles, for his cooperation and influence on the <span corresp="Indians">Indians</span> for their success to send Testimony of this Document for his archive at the Headquarters and to the Quartermaster of said Province; and that he sends notifications of all appropriate mandates for the execution of everything agreed upon to the Commanders of <term n="32">frontier</term> <term n="18" type="untrans">Plazas</term>, <term n="4" type="untrans">Cabildo</term> in the City, and everyone else to whom this pertains in any manner, and with the entirety of these Agreements to report to his Majesty for his Royal intelligence and approval. <span corresp="This_is_how...Government_Scribe">This is how His Excellency provided, mandated, and signed, I hereby certify – <persName n="20">Muñoz</persName>- As mandated by his Excellency- <persName n="12">Judas Tadeo Reyes</persName>, Secretary. In accordance with the original I hereby certify. Santiago, October 18, one thousand eight hundred and three. <lb/><persName n="1">Antonio Garfias</persName><lb/>  
Substitute Government Scribe.</span> </ab></div>  
         
         <div n="30">
            <ab> 
                  <table>
                     <row><cell>SUMMARY</cell><cell></cell></row>
                     <row><cell><term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term> from the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term></cell><cell>239</cell></row>
                     <row><cell><term n="6" type="untrans">Capitanejos</term>, <term n="14" type="untrans">Mozetones</term>, and <term n="24">Warriors</term> of the same</cell><cell>3,060</cell></row>
                     <row><cell>[TOTAL]</cell><cell>3,299</cell></row>
                  </table>
                  <lb/><metamark rend="horizontal-line"/></ab>
         </div>
         
         <div n="31"><ab>Attendees from the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> to the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> amounted to three thousand two hundred and ninety-nine, according to the lists, and notes taken by the <term n="7">Commissioner of Nations and General Language</term> at his arrival to the Encampment, without including the parties who continuously arrived in the following days to the <term n="15" type="untrans">Parla</term>, which could not be accounted for due to the tasks. For the record, we sign, the aforesaid <term n="7">General Commissioner of Nations and General Language</term>, at the <term n="18" type="untrans" >Plaza</term> of Los Ángeles on the eighth of March of one thousand eight hundred and three – <persName n="25">Sebastián Xibaja</persName>- <persName n="3">Fermín Villagrán</persName>.</ab></div><!--whc 01-AUG-2023: waiting to hear back from Pilar about this one: see Word comments-->

         <div n="32"><ab><span corresp="Most_Excellent_Señor">Most Excellent <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term>:</span>   I have the greatest pleasure to offer Your Excellency the appended Record of the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> held in the Field of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> with the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> or Cantons of this <term n="32">Frontier</term>, according to what I presented to Your Excellency in my previous Missive dated the eighth of March shortly after the conclusion of the recent <term n="16" type="untrans">parlamento</term>. Your Excellency proceeded to grant and bestow on me the required Commission, arising from the just motives which prevented personal attendance, by Higher Order on the thirtieth of last October.</ab></div>

         <div n="33"><ab>Even the State indicates the number of Dragoon troops and Militia in attendance at the Encampment. The <span corresp="Indians">Indians</span> are [listed] under <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> or Governments for the understanding of the attendees. <span corresp="Even...positioned">The Diagram will help to provide an overview of the manner in which the offices for the <term n="38">Congress</term> were positioned.</span> Additionally, the Agreements created at that time will serve to inform Your Excellency of the Treaties and confirmations of a general peace negotiated for the benefit of the best Service to the King and for a Partnership guaranteed with the <term n="36">natives</term>, all tendered by the presentation of their promises and recommended charges. However, as the Advisor Doctor  <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="10">Juan Martínez de Rosas</persName> was not present in the celebration as War Auditor, which had been customary in other <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamentos</term>, I trusted <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Brigadier Commander of the Dragoon Troops <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="23">Pedro Nolazco del Río</persName> (as I declared to Your Excellency), because of his expertise and practices, to be involved in all that has been offered. I have reached its conclusion, taking pride in the merits that have proportionally made it [the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>] advantageous, Your Excellency being able to recognize it in its Articles, shortly after the <term n="38">Congress</term>, nothing of superfluous expenses, despite the excessive number of Faction members in attendance, and other worthy situations.</ab></div>

<div n="34"><ab>In compliance with my responsibility, I recommend to Your Excellency the merit that has been acquired by the officers employed to exhaustion during the time of the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>. They acted with the utmost dedication to the duties of the Service, without having given cause for the least reprimand.</ab></div>

<div n="35"><ab>Being informed of all these, Your Excellency will understand the hopes which encourage me to fulfill the Commission with which I was honored, consequently providing you with constant proof of my appreciation, and aspiration with which I hope to take care of the affairs of the Royal Service. On that basis I hope everything accomplished is to the Highest approval of Your Excellency, and it will provide me with the utmost satisfaction.</ab></div>

         <div n="36"><ab>God keep Your Excellency for many years. <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName>, April thirtieth of one thousand eight hundred and three.</ab></div>

<div n="37"><ab><span corresp="His_Excellency...Quijada">His Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>,</span> His Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="14">Luis Muñoz de Guzmán</persName>, Lieutenant General of the Royal Armies, President, <span corresp="Governor">Governor</span>, and Captain General of the <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span> of <placeName>Chile</placeName>.</ab></div>

         <div n="38"><head><span corresp="In_the_City_of_Santiago_de_Chile">In the City of <placeName n="13">Santiago de Chile</placeName></span> on the nineteenth of June of one thousand eight hundred and three: His Excellency <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="14">Luis Muñoz de Guzmán</persName>, Knight of the Order of Santiago, Commander of the towns in the <placeName n="1">Alcántara</placeName>, Lieutenant General of the Royal Army, <span corresp="Governor">Governor</span>, and Captain General of the <span corresp="Kingdom">Kingdom</span> of Chile, President of its <term n="21" type="untrans">Real Audiencia</term>, Superintendent Subdelegate of the <term n="22" type="untrans">Real Hacienda</term> and Post Office, and Royal Vice-Patron, [rubric]:</head></div>

         <div n="39"><ab>Having its Commissioner <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Brigadier <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>, Interim Commander of Arms of the Province of <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName>, with four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term> of that <term n="32">Frontier</term> and Countries of the South witnessed the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> held in the Field of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>, on the days from the third to the fifth of March recently passed, <span corresp="stated...approve">stated: That he ought to approve</span>, and did approve the eight Articles that it contained, with respect to the confirmation of the Treaties and <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamentos</term> previously approved by his Majesty, as relevant for the consolidation of peace, and improved civilization of those <term n="31">nations</term>, and their acknowledgement of the <term n="33">Sovereign</term>, our Catholic King and <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <term n="12" type="untrans">Don</term> <persName n="2">Carlos IV</persName>. And consequently, everything that was established in <span corresp="them">them</span> is to be fulfilled and obeyed in agreement with the <term n="42">governors</term>, <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>, and <term n="26" type="untrans">gilmenes</term> of their corresponding Factions, and <term n="1" type="untrans">Ayllareques</term>, preventing the liberty of mutual trade addressed by the second Article, and all coercion and swindling of <span corresp="Indians">Indians</span>, and the introduction of offensive weapons, wine, and other forbidden products in <span corresp="their_lands">their lands</span> as established by Law twenty-four, title first, book sixth of these provinces in accordance with this same Law, and the following ones up to the thirty-first of the mentioned title and book, and the unusual Regulation created for this reason, and approved by the <term n="3" type="untrans">Real Orden</term> on the ninth of February of seventeen ninety-seven.</ab></div> 
            
            <div n="40"><ab>Regarding personal ambitions expressed by several <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> in that <term n="38">Congress</term>, his Lordship instructed that the <term n="5" type="untrans">cacique</term> of <placeName>Maquegua</placeName> and his associates should be made to understand they ought to resign to the small satisfaction of being able to more easily visit the youth entrusted for their education to the Seminary, [which is] being transferred to the <term n="18" type="untrans" >Plaza</term> of <placeName n="18">Los Ángeles</placeName> due to the greatest advantages resulting from joining the School of Missionary Fathers of the City of <placeName n="6">Chillán</placeName>. There they achieve improved comfort for their livelihood, and the most qualified teachers are assigned, under the direction of the Guardian Father, thus being determined by the King, without intention to alter it, for the many inconveniences of the regulation of both establishments, and greater funding, and outrageous expenses from the new work, which would arise from its repair.</ab></div>

         <div n="41"><ab>That no change be made to the management of the <term n="31">Mission Home</term> of <placeName n="11">Santa Bárbara</placeName>, that had been planned to be abandoned before, but now it will be renovated instead, advancing the Documentation that was postponed, and pending the resolution to be made about this issue in this <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term>, to what pertains to the accomplishment of missions in the <term n="17">Pehuenches</term> Factions, and especially the reestablishment of the [<term n="31">Mission Home</term>] in <placeName>Lolco</placeName>, as requested by its <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>. To that effect, the <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> Quartermaster Military Commander of the Province of <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName> will be in charge. He will ensure its completion, summoning the <span corresp="Councils_of_the_Indians">Councils of the Indians</span> in a timely manner, and consulting this Excellency beforehand about other dispensations that are important to foresee for its preparation, appointing missionaries in accordance to the Father Prefect and Guardian of the <term n="8" type="untrans">Colegio de <placeName n="6">Chillán</placeName></term>, estimating expenses for its establishment, and permanent synods.</ab></div> 
         
         <div n="42"><ab>That the <term n="5" type="untrans">cacique</term> of the <term n="11">Reduction</term> of <placeName n="12">Santa Fé</placeName> be persuaded to cease his demand to have a missionary parish priest like his respectable predecessor the honest elder <persName>Levigueque</persName>, this being a closed matter, and previously decided with the consent of the Illustrious <term n="23" type="untrans">Señor</term> <persName n="21">Bishop of <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName></persName>, who in accordance with the prerogatives of his Authority, and the Pontifical Constitutions, and Institute of Missionaries, which only ought to be employed in the conversion of the heathens, until the <term n="11">reductions</term> are regularized. Regarding the <term n="11">Reduction</term> of <placeName n="12">Santa Fé</placeName>, which due to its longstanding establishment, fully subjected to the <term n="41">bosom of the Church</term>, and located in the Spanish territory, they should glory in their exemption of that ruling, like the ones of <placeName>San Cristóbal</placeName>, and others of similar class subjected to the teaching of the priests <term n="40">instituted</term> by the <term n="39">Ecclesiastical Ordinary</term>, similar in every manner to those of the Spaniards; which I hereby certify.</ab></div>
               
               <div n="43"><ab>
                          <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName>  
                  <lb/><persName n="23">Pedro Nolazco del Río</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="16">Mariano José de Roa</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="11">Juan Zapatero</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="15">Manuel de Vega Bazán</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="22">Pedro José de Benavente</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="18">Melchor de Carvajal</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="13">Luis de la Cruz</persName>
                  <lb/><persName n="19">Miguel Puga</persName>
                  <lb/>Friar <persName n="6">Francisco Javier de Alday</persName>
                  <lb/>Friar <persName n="7">Gil Calvo</persName> Guardian of Chillán
                  <lb/><persName n="8">Gonzalo María de Figueroa</persName>, Secretary of the Commission.</ab></div>


         <div n="44"><ab>In accordance with the <term n="5" type="untrans">Caciques</term>, <term n="42">Governors</term> and individuals, with their <term n="24">Warriors</term> and <term n="14" type="untrans">Mozetones</term> who have attended the General <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">Butalmapus</term>, held on the third day of March of one thousand eight hundred and three.</ab></div> 
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
