<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Negrete 1803: Introduction</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Written by</resp>
               <persName>Pilar Herr</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div><p>The <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of 1803 was notable for its geography, the ceremonial components of the event, and the issues it addressed between the different Mapuche <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> and representatives of the Spanish Crown.</p>
         <p>Geography played a major role in all the <term n="16" type="untrans">parlamento</term> meetings, most notably because it was the physical space where the different representatives from both sides discussed their concerns and wishes. Most <term n="16" type="untrans">parlamento</term> meetings took place in areas both parties considered neutral territory, oftentimes just north or south of the <placeName n="1001">Bío-Bío</placeName> River, which demarcated the northern boundary of Mapuche territory, known as Araucanía. <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> was (and is) a settlement located just south of the <placeName n="1001">Bío-Bío</placeName> River and hosted several <term n="16" type="untrans">parlamentos</term> throughout the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.</p>
            <p>At the <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamento</term> of <placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName> of 1803 there were 3,299 total Mapuches in attendance, with 209 principal <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> representing the four indigenous <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term>, regional areas that loosely represented the various Mapuche groups living in Araucanía. The Crown’s representatives included Brigadier <persName n="24">Pedro Quijada</persName> as General Commander of the Frontier (himself substituting for <persName n="14">Luis Muñoz de Guzmán</persName>, who, as teniente general was too old and unwell to attend), Brigadier general <persName n="23">Pedro Nolazco del Río</persName> as consultant, as well as clergy of the Catholic Church and other <span corresp="Spanish_officials">Spanish officials.</span></p>
            <p>These enormous gatherings were not unusual in the <span corresp="eighteenth_century">eighteenth century</span>. In fact, by the middle of the century, these large, multi-day conferences were the de facto way for the Spanish Crown and the Mapuche communities to maintain open lines of communication and to produce outcomes that, for the most part, avoided outright war and maintained a modicum of coexistence. The Crown financed special foods that included meat, and copious amount of wine, which the guests in attendance (both Spanish and Mapuche) greatly enjoyed. Mapuche <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> gave speeches at specified moments and passed a ceremonial baton from one <term n="5" type="untrans">cacique</term> to another to acknowledge their rank and authority among their respective groups within a <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapu</term>. In other parts of the Spanish empire, such as the southern corners of the Viceroyalty of Peru and the Captaincy of Chile, Spanish domination of indigenous populations was a foregone conclusion. The Chilean <term n="16" type="untrans">parlamentos</term>, however, served as a means by which indigenous representation and agency were constantly negotiated and contested.</p>
            <p>What were the stipulations agreed upon at the Parlamento of 1803? Like other parlamentos before it, the 1803 Parlamento at Negrete began by reaffirming accords that had been agreed upon previously. These included the following: the education of sons of Mapuche governors, <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>, and principals at the <term n="8" type="untrans">Colegio de Propaganda Fide de <placeName n="6">Chillán</placeName></term>; ending disputes and <term n="13" type="untrans">malocas</term> (raids) amongst and between different Mapuche factions within the four <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term>; mandating that members of the <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term> arrest and incarcerate any Spaniard, foreigner, or thief who had committed a crime within <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapu</term> lands; and, finally, that any person who would apprehend and return deserters of the Precinct of <placeName n="17">Valdivia</placeName> to the authorities at the <term n="18" type="untrans" >Plaza</term> of Valdivia would receive twelve pesos in compensation for his efforts.</p>
         <p>As for new accords specific to the 1803 Parlamento of Negrete, Mapuche members of the four <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term>, as good vassals of the Spanish King and Crown, were not permitted to allow any foreigners to trade or "whale hunt" (a euphemism for other non-sanctioned activities) off their coastal lands. They also had to cooperate with Spanish officials and ally with them if war broke out between foreigners and the Spanish. Additionally, the Crown disliked trade between the <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term> and the <term n="30" type="untrans">pampas</term> region of <placeName n="5">Buenos Aires</placeName> (modern day Argentina) and preferred for it to cease altogether. Lastly, the four <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term> had to agree to allow Christian missionaries to come to their lands and to aid them in their missionizing efforts.</p>
         <p>Throughout the five-day ceremony Mapuche <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term>, representing all factions within the four <term n="2" type="untrans">butalmapus</term>, stood up to present their own requests, as well as agree to the accords and express fealty and loyalty to the King.</p>
         <p>Significantly, even though Mapuche <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> were vassals of and expressed fealty to the King, their actions also represented a large degree of autonomy within their own lands. As an example, several <term n="5" type="untrans">caciques</term> declared that Mapuche criminals in Mapuche lands were under Mapuche jurisdiction and therefore could only be arrested and tried under Mapuche law. <term n="16" type="untrans">Parlamentos</term>, then, worked as a mechanism that treated both Mapuche leaders and Crown representatives on equal terms.</p></div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
