<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
    <body>
        
        <div>
            <pb n="219"/>
            <head>Parlamento of<placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>of 1726. ANHCh, FV, vol. 251, fs. 174-193
            </head>
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <head>War Council to transmit the twelve chapters added during the General Congress with the Caciques the 29th of January of 1726
            </head>
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <ab>In the city of <placeName n="7">Concepción</placeName> the twenty-ninth day of the month of January of 1726, The Most Excellent Señor Don Gabriel Cano de Aponte, knight of the Order of <>Alcántara, Knight Commander of Mayorga, member of his Majesty’s Council, Lieutenant General of his royal armies, Governor and Captain-General of this Kingdom, and President of his Royal Tribunal to negotiate and consider matters of the dominion of his Majesty and especially those which concern Peace with the Indians of all the land and the Capitulations and Conditions which they must accept, called to the Accord and Council of War the Persons most expert and intelligent in those matters, including the most Illustrious Señor Bishop of this city, Prelates of the religious orders, and some Missionaries from among those who at the time could be found in this city. All according to their rank will be mentioned in the following manner: <!-- 2025-09-03 D.V.B. Maintaining doc lists as inline text until further instructions. -->= the most Illustrious Reverend Father Francisco Antonio Escandón, most worthy bishop of this city = the Señor Dr. Don Martín de Recabarren of the Council of his Majesty, judge of the Royal Tribunal of this Kingdom and General Legal Advisor for the war = the Señor rector Don Domingo Sarmiento, dean of this holy Catholic Church, Provisor and Vicar General of this bishopric = and the Señores General Commissioner Don Alonzo de Guzmán and Don Alonzo de Figueroa, mayors of this illustrious town council = Don Manuel de Salamanca, General Chief of Staff of the army = Don Juan Fermín Montero de Espinosa, Secretary and Inspector for the King our lord = Don Pedro Rubina, official Royal Accountant of the Treasury = the ordained Reverend Father Brother Francisco Segura Prior of the monastery of the Señor St. Domingo = the Reverend Father retired Lector brother Thomas Crusat Guardian of the monastery of Señor St. Francis = the ordained Reverend Father Brother Manuel de Landaeta Prior of the monastery of St. Augustine = the ordained Reverend Father Brother Pedro de Arenas Knight Commander of the Order of Mercy = the illustrious Reverend Father Juan Manuel Sancho Granado, current Provincial of the Society of Jesus = Father Brother Angelo Carvalli, Prior of St. John of God = the Reverend Father Brother Manuel de Mendoza, former missionary of the order of St. Francis = the Father Joseph María Jess of the Society of Jesus, Provincial Secretary and former missionary = the General Commissioner Don Joseph de Mendoza, in the absence of the current General Commissioner Don Joseph de Arias = the General Commissioner Don Pedro López Asencio, current Captain of Cavalry of the army = the General Commissioner Don Miguel del Solar, also current Captain of Cavalry = the Captain Don Pedro de Yllanes, Inspector of the Infantry of the army = and Don Manuel Cabrito Sargeant, Major of this fortress and being gathered in this manner in the royal buildings of the palace, dwelling place of the aforementioned Señor Governor Captain 
            <pb n="220"/>                
                General, His Excellency stated that as it is well-known to those present and other neighbors and inhabitants of this Kingdom that His Majesty has spent and consumed from his Royal estate and Patrimony a great many Pesos on the conquest and determined warfare that has continued for so many years with the barbarous Indians: it is also well known that even though the Indians, having suffered epidemics, for many years kept the peace, but not such a secure peace that there had not been a few disturbances, which at all times required the Señores Governors my predecessors to take up arms to punish the rebellions and insults that they had committed. And it is evident that, during the governorship of this realm of the Señor Don Juan Andrés de Uztariz of the Order of Santiago, they attempted rebellion in the year 1715 and, because it expanded, matters proceeded to the punishment of some of its initiators with the death penalty. There went on to be a parlamento in the location of Tapihue, which did not succeed in calming their spirits such that they did not desist from the attempted uprising; rather, as may be inferred from the present operations of the Indians, the volcano in their hearts was preserved until in the year 1723 it exploded, with them taking up arms shamefully, killing Captains of Amigos1 and stirring up revolt in the whole land at once. Although the Indians of the coast remained seemingly neutral for a few months, later they also followed the Conspiracy, besieging the people of the plains of Purén who were poorly supplied with that which is needed for defense. Don Manuel de Salamanca, General Chief of Staff of the army went, in the harshest part of Winter, to rescue the aforesaid military stronghold with a few more than four hundred men whom he was soon able to muster against the multitude of five or six thousand Indians, whom they had learned had intended to hamper their departure, which they ultimately completed without the least opposition. They then achieved their retreat in the same, leaving the aforesaid stronghold reinforced with people, munitions, and supplies. I had this relief operation repeated afterward, having been stationed with a group of people on the Camino de Sante Fe on the banks of the Bío Bío to support the Chief of Staff and to oppose any initiative of the Indians and, in case it were necessary, to aid the aforesaid stronghold, against which they made repeated assaults over the course of the winter, carrying out others at the same time at the forts of Tucapel, Nacimiento, and Santa Juana, which I aided, prevailing over obstacles, as is evident by the fact that they could maintain their garrisons, overcoming with their constancy and valor the expectation that the Indians would sacrifice them until, the next Spring, I made the Indians dismiss that expectation, bringing my men to the stronghold of Purén for this purpose. The most important part of my duties was the preservation of the Kingdom in peace and calm so that all its inhabitants and, what is more, those selfsame Indians, could gain the benefits thereof. Today [the Indians] find themselves deprived [of those benefits] by the rebellion..." . I have arranged things according to the Royal Letter of December 30, 1724 in which his Majesty, having received news of these events, commanded me to pardon them in his Royal name and to listen to the Entreaties that they have repeatedly made to ask that I give them the Peace which they long for, having been chastened by the miseries they suffer and the disquiet in which the noise of Warfare and the anxiety of being attacked keeps them. But, in order to celebrate the Pardon under the conditions that will best maintain the illustrious honor of the military prowess and reputation of the Spaniards, and by the means that will best facilitate teaching and Christian Instruction for the purpose of the propagation of the Holy Gospel, which as a supernatural cause and service to God should be the first object of further efforts and is the goal toward which his Majesty not only directs continuous recommendations but spreads his innumerable 
                <pb n="221"/>
                riches, and so that by all means evangelical Ministers may arrive to them and, exiling the darkness of their blindness and false rites, may make them see the unfailing light of the true religion under which they should live and through which alone they may be saved, the following conditions have seemed to me conducive and even necessary so that everything may be obtained for the greater honor and glory of God and our King and lord.</ab>
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <ab>1. That they must lay down their arms and dissolve whatever pacts, provisions or regulations they may have; that they should not be eager to continue the war; that they must profess that they are vassals of the king and that they had no reason to take up arms and that at no time will the wrongs that they have supposedly suffered be reason to do so, rather that they will be obliged to communicate them to the Spanish authorities and superiors who will administer justice to them and make amends by punishing those who aggrieved them. If those same authorities should fail to comply with this obligation, they will bring their grievances to me or to the lord Governors who will succeed me in my office (as I do not doubt that the officials who succeed me will do the same), and I offer to administer justice and punish the transgressors in the name of the King. 
                
                2. That because of this condition they must be the friends of my friends and enemies of my enemies and that they must not permit by their favor, help, or shelter that anyone give us trouble, wrong, or damage, whether it be Indians, wicked Spaniards, or foreigners who could be introduced. Rather, the Indians will help us to guard against the wrongs that could threaten them just like the Spaniards do, in such a way that it will be understood in this provision that crimes must be punished. The Indians will do this by handing over all the Spaniards, mestizos, blacks, or mulattos that, having committed crimes in our Lands should pass over to theirs to avoid punishment, and the Indians must present to the authorities or Commanders of the army those of their people who should commit crimes so that they may be punished, being understood that they will be looked upon with kindness and that without the correction of evildoers and respect for the good there can neither be a secure peace nor a heart that faithfully preserves a friendship. 
                
                3. As a short time ago during this uprising it was considered convenient to withdraw those fortifications which were found on the other side of the Biobío, His Majesty has been informed and it will be left to my discretion, as it seems convenient based on the state of things, to rebuild them in the same places or in others better suited to the benefit and protection of those same Indians; or whether his Majesty commands that they be rebuilt as a matter of course, in which case they must be restored without the least contradiction or repugnance, nor should they cause any surprise as they are expressly accepted in this provision and the Indians in whichever Jurisdiction the work should take place must be obliged to come together to perform the work and the caciques must make them help with the rebuilding and the Spanish to maintain them with the sustenance that is customary when mandatory labor is required. 
                
                4. And that which is of most concern is that the teaching of the Christian doctrine and the arrival when convenient of the missionary Friars for the Baptism and teaching of the Youth and the spiritual council of the adults must be received freely and without resistance, that they must be accepted and venerated with the respect with which we the Spaniards grant them and which is owed to the Ministers of God through whose voices they will understand that which will make them children of God and save them if with their divine help they should receive in their hearts the one who sends them, who is God himself, for their benefit; which benefit the King most seeks and desires that they obtain; and in order that this be obtained with a happy outcome it will be best that they Place their small children of both sexes as if in school giving them to those same missionary Friars, secure that they will not be placed in service other than that of the Christian Teaching and policy that for no reason will they be taken out of the power of the Fathers nor will they leave their territories unless it is the Fathers’ will, about which I and the other secular Ministers will take the greatest care as well as the greatest diligence that was customary for the Superiors of the Sacred Society of Jesus or of any other Religion that should have a mission on the earth as had our Father Saint Francis in whose care are the missions, such that by the treatment and the effects they will inevitably come to know the special benefit and utility that they gain from the fact that the boys and girls are educated in this manner and they must not consider a surprise or an affront the correction that the Friars may judge necessary for teaching because this will never exceed that which any biological Father and God our Father practices on his children and disciples for their own good and that truly consists of the best management. 
                
                5. That the Adults who become Baptized will not close their ears to the helpful advice of the missionary Friars; rather that as long as they are called discreetly so they may attend without great inconvenience to their labors they will come together to learn about and understand the law they profess, by which means they will achieve the benefit of being good-naturedly Christian and they will become capable of receiving the Holy Sacraments, through which door they should enter into Heaven and will imperceptibly understand the human fragility which pushes them not just into sin but into these rebellions and restlessness which brings with it many other sins. 
                
                6. That because the grievances that have given motive for rebellions are constantly born from gatherings because these are organized secretly, without public authorization, in complete contradiction of the laws which exist and should be kept in favor of the Indians, it will be convenient that these gatherings should be freely held but the times in which they are celebrated in designated places should be reduced as they find convenient to three or four fairs per year or as many as they judge necessary and that they should request that the Indians and Spaniards come together with their merchandise on a certain day and place where the authority and another person or persons whom the Spaniards will name, as well as that same authority and those people whom the Indians will name and if it seems fitting to the Illustrious Provincial Friars Superior of the missions, a Missionary Friar elected by those who are at the missions at the time shall also attend so that in view of these people the merchandise shall be recognized, the Prices shall be established, and the agreements or bargains that are being contracted in this way, are fulfilled faithfully from hand to hand, it being understood that the authorities that are involved in this in addition to taking great interest, by their conscience will equally punish excess, for fraud, for favoritism or personal interest in any deceit that should be discovered and that as a matter of course, apart from the arbitrary sentences that I reserve to my judgment and that of the lord Governors that succeed me, they shall be deprived of those employments and honors that they enjoy and obliged to make restitution for the damages they have caused to the party that has suffered them to remove all cause for complaint and it should be in case and by no means should be permitted on credit, which can allow the insufficiency of the debtors. 
                
                7. And because at all times the greatest cause of rebellions has been a practice execrable and contrary to the divine, human and royal rights, the buying and selling of Free people like the Indians are, no Spaniard will be so bold under threat of legal Punishment to acquire an object of this title as they call the practice, with which name they defraud all the regulation of the law and commit a grave sin and causes the vexation that it brings as a consequence, like Rebellions, thefts, deaths, fires, and ruins. After this is done by any Spaniard of any social status, quality or condition, who is either the Father or Relatives of the Indian woman or man, the boy or girl that should be connived against in this manner who should be obliged to declare it but also equally and Foremost the cacique in whose reducción it should occur must take care to give an account so that the transgressor may be punished and the Object may be restored to their liberty. I beg and request that the Reverend Missionary Friars Practice in this matter their charity giving accounts of these excesses, reassuring them that it will be understood that in those cases which on account of their information the wrong will be corrected the punishments will be mitigated so that the aforesaid Reverend Friars will not be reluctant to declare information about them and because these purchases are not regularly made without the consent of the Parents or relatives. In this contract I declare that this practice will not benefit the buyers and that when Parents should voluntarily wish to give over their sons or daughters to be raised and taught by and to serve the Spaniards they can do so but it must be by the permission and of the authority who will be found at the gatherings and only at this time. The name of the person who is being given over, as well as that of his verified Father or relative who, according to custom, may decide that person’s fate, must be written in a Book that the authority will have for the purpose, along with who receives the person and where they reside so that it may be recognized and it will be easy to learn how that person treats them and at all times receive new of them and assure that they pay what is legally owed from gathering to gathering, returning the person as often as the parents request them and if the person voluntarily, as has been said, wishes to return or if they are not satisfied with their service, nor can they be prevented from marrying according to the rules of our Holy Mother Church when they wish and when the Parish approves. 
                
                8. And so that all the difficulties that are wished for in this peace treaty may be made smooth and free of obstacles, because in the previous provision the door was closed to the buying and selling of Free People, it has been judged necessary to prevent the enslavement of married Indian women who, lacking conjugal fidelity, have committed adultery, and who by the inalterable custom of the Indians are punished with a Death Sentence that their own husbands execute, that which for many years in these parts they have not practiced because they replace the rigors of the death sentence with that of slavery, selling the women to the Spaniards; who have had the permission [redacted] of Theologians because they saved their lives. In future instances they may justifiably employ the same measure of giving them to the Spaniards for the Payments that should correspond to them according to custom, and the Spaniards should receive them not with the power and dominion of a perpetual master but to be served by her for the corresponding time according to what they should moderately enjoy from her service, which must be determined by the Justices of the territory where she resides; on account of this they will be obliged to declare her as soon as they bring her into a city or location, bringing the paper from the authority of the fort where she should be received to be taken from for this reason that justifies holding her; and the authorities of the forts will take special care that those who are handed over under this pretext are women capable of matrimony and that, for those who are and whom the Indians wish to hand over, it should be for the reason that gives rise to this permission. 
                
                9. And so that all justifications for fraud, further provisions, and the continual complaints that are expressed in these provisions, no Spaniard, mestizo, mulatto, black person, or other person whatever who may wander around this part of the Bio Bio may enter into Indian land either alone or accompanied unless ordered to so by the Chiefs on errands for the Royal service; this is in case harm should come from the delay in reporting to me or to the Secretary Inspector who should give these Permissions; and it will be the obligation of the authority who for the aforesaid reason to report immediately expressing the motive for which he sent them so that they may not be part of any plots; because if on the contrary they are, the parties will be gravely punished and taken away from the frontier on the first offense and on the second thrown out of the Kingdom for being harmful to the public peace, which consists of good order and treatment between the Spaniards and the Indians. This is regarding Spaniards, and for those who are not Spaniards the punishment will be two hundred lashes for the first offense and exile to the Isla de la Piedra. 
                
                10. For as this peace treaty is conducted for the purposes that up until this point have been expressed, in which one very principal one is the comfort of those same Indians, and as these Indians often go to work in the Districts of this Kingdom in which those within the Districts will not cease to suffer vexations because of the disorder and poor accounting with which the Indians enter, the permission to move around is given to them, but those who travel must present themselves to one of the frontier regiments, whose authorities will have Books in which their names and the places they are going will be set down and will give them, according to where they are going, a paper which contains the names of those who are traveling to each district in which they will go to serve, according to their free will, whomever they wish. But he who receives them will have a precise obligation to make it known as soon as possible, along with the terms of agreement and the responsibility for satisfying them, to the Mayor of the district or one of his lieutenants so that they may back him up and write it down in in a special Book that they will have for this purpose. By these means one will avoid the complaint that they have not been paid and the Indians of the land will be recognized exempt from tribute, so that it may not be exacted from them nor permitted that the landlords give them the least vexation for this reason, thus making their mode of work easier. If the Indians should wander about from district to district and for this reason should suffer offenses, in spite of these helpful provisions, it will be your fault and may not be able to be remedied (although it will always be tried) with the exactitude which is desired. And it is warned that in none of these transactions will the Authorities or Mayors have rights to the Indians and that no person from the districts can put them into service unless it is preceded by the circumstance explained here. 
                
                11. That for the damages mutually received their must be a general pardon; neither will the Spaniards ask for the return of things that have been stolen from the Indians nor will these seek satisfaction from the Spaniards, and they must control themselves going Forward in that which regards the thefts which until now they have Practiced. If a theft should be done it must be punished, and those same caciques will have the obligation to return the goods. For the fact that they are at this moment able to keep things that belong to the Spaniards and have been capitulated as I offer by Word of the King, it will not be a justification to abuse this kindness, nor should it give the Spaniards, for the purpose of defending their livestock, a reason to cause friction with them and deaths and disruption. They should reassure themselves that as soon as they conform to this agreement, they will immediately be less exposed to the miserable state of war to which these errors conduct them. In the case that some Indians of the land may be caught stealing in our lands, the Indians must understand that the evildoers will be punished with the legal penalties and this demonstration of Justice must not be an occasion for resentment; rather, if the aggressors should return to Indian land the caciques must hand them over so that Justice may be done. And so that equality may be conserved in this arrangement, if any Spaniards should come into their lands to disturb them and steal their Goods, they must very soon tell the closest authorities so that they may take the Measure of extracting them and punishing them, the Indians understanding that it will be to their advantage to conceal this as little as possible. 
                
                12. That the authorities of the forts may not deny permission to the Indians to go in an appropriate number to speak with the Lord Governor, the Most Illustrious Lord Bishop, the Secretary Inspector, or any other of the Principal Leaders of the army, on pain of which they may be deprived of their employment if it is proven to be to the contrary.                 
                
                
                <div>
                    <ab>Vista y considerado por el Ylustrisimo Señor obispo Reberendos Padres y demas señores que compusieron la Junta las Propuestas de admitir los yndios a las passes y las Capitulaciones discu[rridas] por el Excelentisimo señor Pressidente parecio ser comforme a la voluntad de su Magestad en beneficio comun de el Reino el sosiego que por ella se conseguira y asi mismo jusgaron las Capitulaciones dignas del celo con que su excelencia se aplica a mantener y concervar en equidad y Justicia los naturales del Reino y las mas proporcionadas a este fin y segura en conciencia su practica por lo que fueron de parecer unanimes y conformes se estableciese con ellas la paz lo firmaron en este papel comun a falta del sellado de que doy fee.</ab>
                </div>
                
                <!-- 2024-02-18 amz List of names, to be added later from bottom of 224/top 225 | 2024-02-19 amz Format as div/ab/<list rend="simple">, preserve empty spaces as empty <item>s, add column break as comment for now, "ante" lines as one block of inline text with <lb/> -->
                <div><ab><list rend="simple">
                    <item>Don Gabriel Cano</item>
                    <item/>
                    <item>Martin de Recabarren</item>
                    <item>Don Alonso de Guzman</item>
                    <item>Don Alonso de Cordova y Figueroa</item>
                    <item>Don Manuel de Salamanca</item>
                    <item>Manuel Sancho Granados</item>
                    <item>Pedro Robina</item>
                    <item>Manuel Cabrito</item>
                    <item>Manuel de Landaeta</item>
                    <item>Prior y Vic. Provincial</item>
                    <item>Fermin Montero De Espinossa</item>
                    <item>Joseph de Mendoza y Salaberr[--]</item>
                    <item>Don Miguel de el Solar</item>
                    <!-- COLUMN BREAK -->
                    <item>Francisco Antonio Escandon</item>
                    <item>Obispo de la Concepción</item>
                    <item/>
                    <item>Fray Tomas Cruzat</item>
                    <item>Prior Francisco Segura</item>
                    <item>Pedro de Arenas</item>
                    <item>Don Pedro de Illanez</item>
                    <item>Joseph M. Jessaf</item>
                    <item>Don Joseph Arias</item>
                    <item>Don Pedro Lopez Asencio</item>
                    <!-- 2024-03-03 amz NOTE: Columns are uneven, 4 blank spaces on right -->
                </list></ab></div>
                
                <div>
                    <ab>Ante my
                        <lb/>Don Thomas Valdes
                        <lb/>Secretario de Gobierno</ab>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <ab>A orillas del <placeName n="1001">Rio de Biobio</placeName> sitio de<placeName n="8">Negrete</placeName>en treze dias del mes de febrero de mil setecientos y beinte y seis años el excelentisimo señor Don Gabriel Cano de Aponte Cavallero de el orden de<placeName n="1">Alcantara</placeName>Comendador de Mayorga de el Consejo de Su Magestad Theniente general de sus Reales exercitos Governador y Capitan General de este reino y Pressidente de su Real audiencia en virtud de la Junta y Acuerdo General preinserto con asistencia del Ilustrisimo P. señor Don Francisco Antonio Escandon del Consejo de su Magestad obispo de la Ciudad de la<placeName n="7">Concepcion</placeName>de el señor Lizenciado Don Martin de Recabarren asi mismo del Consejo de su Magestad oydor de la Real Audiencia de este Reino y auditor general de la guerra de el Reverendisimo Padre Manuel Sancho Granado de la Compañia de Jesus Provincial de esta Provincia de Don Manuel de Salamanca Maestre de Campo General de el Real exercito de Don Ambrosio Lovillo Comisario General de la Cavalleria de el y de otras personas asi padres misioneros de la Compañía de Jesus y otros Religiosos de san Francisco y San Agustin como de comisarios de la Cavalleria Reformados capitanes de Cavalleria e Infanteria actuales del exercito para efecto de poner en ejecucion el Parlamento que se conzedio libre el passo de Biobio a los yndios conducidos por el R. P. Diego de Amaia de la Compañia de Jesus y misionero que ha sido muchos años en estas misiones y con efecto les pu[so] de esta Parte ynmediatos a los quarteles de españoles desarmados y el dia onse y dose juntos y congregados los caciques Millaleubu = Calbuqueupu Dugulab que lo son de la Reducion de<placeName n="2">Angol</placeName>Coliquerupu = Quidquen = Minchellanca = Quntrulabquen = Carilabquen = Marileubu = Colinamun = Tehuaiquilabquen = Marimañque = Painetaru = Chiguaini = Quidequeupu = Marillanca = Caoñancu = Cadupichun = Quilaleubu = Igaitaru = Guenchuleubu = Tanmaleubu = Guenchulican = Lincobilu = Pormallanca = Piuquillanca = Chañabilu = Yamelicheuque = Rapimañ[que] = Quntecura = Penchulebi = Caniuantu = Alecoyam = Alcabilu = Ygaitar = [Ra]guimañque = Naguelbilu = Paillayecu = Painemalin = Ancayecu = Millaleubu = Chiguaypillan = Guenteleubu = Cayuquipu = Peupuantu = Cayuñamen = Melipilan Paillalmapu = Regalqueupu = Chiguaicura = Duguleb = Catiñancu = Cayuñamcu = Licanqueupu = Epullanca = Cañirequeupu = Ancatemu = Tipailabquen = Don Alonso Naguel Guala = Calbucheuque = Colliguala = Millaquiga = Mariquilpe = Ancatemu = Anicoyam = Llanquiñancu = Mañquebudu = Calcumilla = Callbuquirque = Guayquinaguel = Guenchuguere = Remulcaguin = Guilimaña = Curamilla = Cayupange = Aucaguere = Guechacoy = Guenchuguala= Pichilame = Curilemu = Naguelguala = Tureunaguel = Curilafquen = Millalabquen = Llanca Naguel = Guentenaguel = Chañaleubu = Guenuquirqi = Caripaqy = Guenupaqi = Mañquebudi = Llicanantai = Changuey = Caticura = Piutimilla = Pelquileubu = Huenchunaguel = Guente Cura = Guentecura = Reguecaguin = Cayupi = Raginaguel = Marinaguel = Lipileubu = Neculqueupu = Pai
                        <pb n="226"/>
                        llabudu= Lipiantu = Quelipi = Guentecura = Guaiquiguin =Antuum = Huehuelanco = Guaquinpagi = Melitacum = Paillaguala = Antupillan = Colipillan = Melg[ramaña]Naguelguala = Mariñancu = Lienantu = Negueyantu = Bilumañque = Calbuantu = Guayquilafquen = Antillanca = Callucupil = Tangolafquen = Rapillanca = Ñancuantu = Ñirriantu = Marilebi = Ranquilegui = Incocheuque = Caupichun = Guayquipangui = Cariopichun = Lonconaguel = Catiyere = Namuncura = Amgollanca = Guayquihuenu = Callilebi = Llancamacha = Naguecollan = Paillaquirque = Guincolafquen = Manquelabquen = Pichilemu = Guncalebi = en presencia de su excelencia y los señores de su asistencia oye por los quatro Gutammapus quatro Caciques que fueron Don Miguel Melitacum = Don Juan Millaleubu = Tureunau = y Leboepillan = a la usanza de ellos sobre los Puntos y Caussas que pudieron mober el alsamiento general en que han estado y requirieron los referidos quatro casiques por su horden a todos los demas que se allaron presentes para que cada uno si tubiese que decir lo hisiese y avibando a todos con eficacia al arrepentimiento de su desacierto el qual fue reprehendido antesedentemente por el excelentisimo señor Governador por medio del Capitan Pedro de Sotomaior Pedreros que hizo oficio de Ynterprete General quien juro por Dios nuestro Señor y una señal de cruz en forma de derecho de usar bien y fielmente el dicho oficio de tal ynterprete y se redujo a manifestar Generalmente por caussa los agravios que havian padesido de los Capitanes de Amigos que tenian en sus Reduciones que les repetian las Vejaciones de quitarles los hijos y las hijas estraiendolos por negosiacion propia de la potestad de sus padres para venderlos a la usanza sin contribuirles con las pagas que deven darles segun su estilo sobre que prosedian si reclamaban a darles de palos amarrarlos y molestarlos siendo la mayor que les hacian no permitirles pasar a quejarse al señor Governador y Maestre de Campo General ni otros Gefes del ejercito cuya opresion les obligo al Yerro que havian cometido de que benian ya pesarosos por que se avian desengañado que ni el señor Governador ni el Maestre de campo Havian concurrido a su mal sino mentiras de los mismos capitanes para atemorizarlos y quitarles el recurso y con efecto refirieron algunos casos y exzesos y un papel de el Maestre de Campo dirigido para su amparo a un Capitan de amigos que no tubo otro efecto por entonsses que yrritarle mas y que haora que havian tenido la fortuna y el gusto de conoserlos toda la tierra por que todos los caciques principales de ella sin eseptuarse mas que dos Antenau por enfermo y Quricabilu por lo biejo dejaban de estar en este parlamento aunque embiaron sus hijos para su representacion los tenian por nuevos Padres y que esperaban que como a hijos los avian de mirar pues avian benido hasta tan lejos solo por quitarles los alborotos y males de la guerra y por falta de la comunicacion de los españoles benian y pidieron que por lo mucho que havian trabajado para este parlamento el Maestre de Campo Don Manuel de Salamanca y comisario Don Ambrosio Lovillo les mantubiese su Excelencia en sus empleos para que fuesen atendidos de el como hasta aqui lo havian experimentado: y atendida la buena disposicion que generalmente se vio en todos las eficacia de sus deseos la confecion de sus yerros y los propocitos que manifestaron de labarlos con la buena fee y legalidad que prometieron aviendoseles hecho saver por el sargento maior Don Jorge Fontalvez quien juro por Dios nuestro Padre y una señal de cruz en forma de derecho de usar bien y fielmente el oficio de ynterprete las Capitulaciones y nuevas reglas con que se establecia esta paz y acreditose a la segunda el que los yndios de la costa siempre que avistasen ellos Navio estrangero han de retirar tierra adentro a competente distancia sus Ganados que resistirán El desembarco e yntroducion de Gentes estrangeras y avissaran luego luego a los cavos del exercito para que les aiuden a defenderese y que no les ostilisen y sobre todas otra capitulacion para quitar toda leve ocacion de quebrantar la presente paz que deve ser firme por fundarse en la maior combeniencia y conservacion de los yndios en la possision de su livertad y vienes. Se declaro quedar en su fuersa y vigor la ynalterada
                        <pb n="227"/>
                        costumbre de benir los casiquez y los particulares siempre que fuesen llamados por los señores Governadores de este Reino o por los Gefes maiores de el exercito y cabos de el y assimismo quedar obligados a dar la mita para las obras de el Rey como se ha observado por Capitulacion ynbariable de todos los Parlamentos y esta mita se ha de dar del butammapu a que correspondiese el lugar donde han de servir dandoseles por parte de el Rey el mantenimiento que en semejantes ocaciones tienen señalado y asegurandoles no se usare de la mita para otro fin el que el expresado y variandole qualquier cabo y oficial sera castigado y si les defraudaren el mantenimiento y que los cabos no podran pedir mita sin horden de los Señores Governadores o Maestre de Campo General si para esto se le diese facultad especial comprehendiendose este Capitulo y obligacion que han de dar los yndios Mita de los quatro Butammapus que si se ofreciese alguna otra faena de todos en que se tendra la atencion de no gravar a uno solo sin hacer repartimiento con equidad en todos y entendidas por todos desatadas las dudas que se les ofreciezen sobre algunas haviendo juicio que heran terminadas a restableserles el sosiego perdido librarles de agravios y mantenerlos en equidad y Justicia: unanimes las admitieron y publicaron serles provechosas: en cuya concequensia hecha por todos la señal de la cruz y adbertidos de la fuerza de el Juramento en vas[allaje] prometieron guardarlas y observarlas y arreglandose en todo a sus dispociciones y devajo de el mismo Juramento bolbieron a confesar el vasallaje y prometer al Rey nuestro señor que Dios g[uarde] fidelidad y con muchas demostraciones de regocijo se serro el acto no haviendo firmado los casiques por no saber y lo firmo Su Excelencia con los demas señores de la asistencia de que doy fee = En este papel comun por no aver de sellado =</ab>
                </div>
                
                <!-- 2024-02-18 amz List of names, to be added later from bottom of 227 | 2024-02-19 amz Format as div/ab/<list rend="simple">, preserve empty spaces as empty <item>s -->
                <div><ab><list rend="simple">
                    <item>Gabriel Cano</item>
                    <item>Martin de Recabarren</item>
                    <item>Manuel Sancho Granados</item>
                    <item>Diego Amaya</item>
                    <item>Fray Juan Murillo Capellan maior del Reyno</item>
                    <item>Don Joseph de Mendoza</item>
                    <item>Don Pedro de condores</item>
                    <item>Joseph de Roa</item>
                    <item>Francisco de Baldes</item>
                    <item>Manuel Cabrito</item>
                    <item>Domingo Leon</item>
                    <item>Jorge Fontalvez</item>
                    <item>Francisco Antonio Obispo de la Concepcion</item>
                    <item>Don Manuel de Salamanca</item>
                    <item>Ambrosio Lobillo</item>
                    <item>Fray Joseph Escan[-]</item>
                    <item>Francisco Xavier Bolfisen</item>
                    <item>Francisco Navarro y Roa</item>
                    <item>Miguel de Rod[riguez]</item>
                    <item>Don Pedro illanes</item>
                    <item>Don Pedro Lopez de Asencio</item>
                    <item>Joseph Cruzatt</item>
                    <item>Manuel de Mardones</item>
                    <item>Pedro oya[--]</item>
                    <item>Don Thomas</item>
                </list></ab></div>
                
                <div>
                    <ab>Damos fee que Don Thomas Valdes [---]</ab>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <pb n="228"/>
                    <ab>El Instrumento de la Foxa de enfrente parese ya autorizado fue escrivano de Govierno de este Reyno como se intitula en el tiempo que le Goberno el Excmo señor Don Gabriel Cano cavallero del horden de<placeName n="1">Alcantara</placeName>Comendador de Mayorga en el dicho horden Theniente General de los Reales Exercitos de su Magestad Governador y Capitan de este Reyno de Chille y pressidente de su Real Audiencia y se le dio entera fee y credito en juicio y fuera del y que conste damos la presente en la ciudad de<placeName n="13">Santiago de chile</placeName>en ciete dias del mes de hen[ero] de mil seteccientos y quarenta</ab>
                </div>
                
                <!-- 2024-02-18 amz List of names, to be added later from middle of 228 | 2024-02-19 amz Format as div/ab/<list rend="simple">, preserve empty spaces as empty <item>s, add column breaks as comment for now -->
                <div><ab><list rend="simple">
                    <item>En testimonio de Verdad
                        <lb/>Juan Baptista de Borda
                        <lb/>Escribano Publico y
                        <lb/>Real Hacienda</item>
                    <!-- COLUMN BREAK -->
                    <item>En Testimonio de Verdad
                        <lb/>Santiago de San [---]
                        <lb/>Escribano Publico y
                        <lb/>de [---]</item>
                    <!-- COLUMN BREAK -->
                    <item>Juan de Morales
                        <lb/>Escribano Publico y
                        <lb/>Real Hacienda</item>
                </list></ab></div>
                
                <div>
                    <ab>[Firmas]</ab>
                </div>
    </body>
</text>